How long are we
going to stay here?
I thought we were
going to the border.
How should I know?
There will probably be many soldiers who will be confused and won't follow orders.
It will mean some sporadic fighting,
but we will keep the casualties to a minimum.
We are now going to
return to Central.
With the troops we have at present, we will
take control of the Central Command Center.
You're planning to
stage a revolt?!
You'd rebel against the Führer?!
The Führer and those around him have used the country for their own purposes
and led us down the wrong path!
We'll take control of the Assembly at the same time.
But this is all so sudden,
and without any evidence...
Evidence?
Here is your evidence!
There isn't a single flaw in this well-trained body of mine.
This is my evidence
that my words are true!
Go on, go on, look at it!
Touch it! See for yourself!
Go on, go on.
Go on!
The Philosopher's Stone.
Those who obtain it are set free from the Law of Equivalent Exchange.
There is no need to pay a price
in order to obtain something, either.
We sought it and found it.
Mama!
I restructured your water into ethanol.
It vaporizes at room temperature.
Well done...
Make sure you tidy up when you're finished...
Ed, Al...
Winry?
What's wrong?
Did something happen in the village?
I came because I was concerned.
You finally took care of her, huh?
You're not her...
Al, you're the one I really love!
This is where it ends.
It's no use.
I'm the Philosopher's Stone.
So I hear.
Well then, shall we try this out?
If you've become
the Philosopher's Stone,
then you should still be perfectly fine
if I destroy this here.
Stop! Don't you touch Al!
You don't have to worry.
I'm just going to carry him to you-know-who's place.
"You-know-who"?
The one Lust was talking about?
The one who controls you
and for whom you're seeking the Philosopher's Stone to make immortal?
Maybe so,
although it's not as though you have absolutely nothing to do with that person.
By any chance,
is the person above you
the one who deliberately
enticed our mom
and did those things to her?
It couldn't be!
There's no way Dad would do those things!
Okay, let's go.
Hey, you've got the wrong guy!
Go slow him down!
That guy can do anything, right?
You're not allowed to touch him.
I can use him to bring Mama back!
Isn't that right?!
Enough already!
Al!
This is your fault.
It's your fault that Mama is gone!
Stop!
Mama's gone! Mama's gone!
Mama's gone!
She was your mama too!
Stop!
I don't have anything
to do with you.
I'm the one you want to kill.
You're not my mama!
I've got nothing to do with you!
Sensei!
Are you okay?
He cried.
I couldn't bring myself to cry.
And yet, he did.
It's as if he was doing it
on my behalf.
You've had enough.
Right now, it's about Al.
I should be of some help,
such that I am.
That's why I'm here.
Brother, we need to get going.
Hold on, hold on!
That's Central for you.
There are lots of books here I've never even seen!
They've even got this?!
And this too!
I can't wait to see Ed and Al.
Don't you have enough?
Uh-oh, if I pick these up, we won't be able to afford a room tonight.
But if I don't get them now, there's no telling when I can get them again.
On my tab?
No, sir.
This shop specializes in books for our regular customers, the State Alchemists.
You couldn't understand
what you'd read in these anyhow.
On...
On my State Alchemist's tab.
To tell you the truth...
Brother?
Is this him? Edward Elric?
Yes, he definitely identified himself as the Fullmetal Alchemist.
W-Wait a minute! I was just joking around!
I'm really—
Tell us all about it at
the Command Center.
There are orders to place you in custody as soon as you're found.
Brother, what's going on?
Keep back, Fletcher!
It's his brother!
The younger Elric brother is here!
Hold it! Come on!
Don't struggle!
Brother!
Huh? Was the younger brother the shorter one?
Well, of course he is!
What did you do, Brother?
Central is a scary place.
Lust...
You sealed the homunculus?
It wasn't me.
It was probably...
In any case, that means
there are four of them left:
the child, the one who eats everything,
the one who can transform into anything,
and the Führer.
And the one who's above them.
Who's there?!
Nina, say hello.
What's the matter?
Are you bashful? I see...
Her soul didn't come back, then?
Nina, shall we play?
I know! Where's Alexander?
Where did Alexander go?
What are we going to do with him?
Right, Nina?
Are you sure about this?
She's a soulless doll.
That is the form
his sin has taken on.
He's going to go on living,
embracing that.
That's good enough for me.
You've grown up, huh?
Grown up?
I was sure I grew up when I decided to become a State Alchemist.
Well then, what are
you going to do?
I only know where one of
the remaining homunculi is.
The Führer, King Bradley.
What are you doing?!
Hurry it up!
We're completely surrounded.
There were even fewer soldiers
who followed us than we expected.
Nothing we can do about that.
The Führer's authority is absolute.
There aren't many officers who would go against it.
So, our new Brigadier General's plan was faulty.
No, Mustang's plan
was to buy time here
and get Central's soldiers
to head this way.
Right now, we just have to hang in there for a bit.
Maj—Lt. Colonel!
Are you sure about me presuming to act like this, when I'm not even Brigadier General Mustang?
Keep your chin up.
I am here with you.
Besides,
it looks good on you.
No, you can't, Lieutenant Havoc...
Can I get you to keep
your mouth closed?
Yes. This must be some important work you're doing, right?
It's a top-secret mission. Make sure you don't mention it to anyone.
Sorry.
Not at all...
What are you angry about?
I'm not angry.
Looks like Havoc and the others succeeded in making their move.
Yes.
Hurry, hurry, hurry!
Our whole force has to catch up to
Brigadier General Mustang's division tonight!
Impressive, being able to organize your division as quickly as that.
I owe it all to your orders, Führer.
To think that you supposed that
such a circumstance as this would arise!
It is now established that if Mustang and Armstrong are given some military force,
they are sure to launch a revolt,
which makes them agitators,
the same as Basque Grand was.
I had to promote him to Brigadier General
to make it look like I trusted him.
You men must have been
quite discontent about that.
Of course not!
We will put them down and return within a day or two!
Can I go home for the day?
Oh, some boys using the name of the
Elric brothers were arrested this morning.
Hmm, let's see...
Dispose of them.
Why did you say
you were Edward Elric?
What was I supposed to do? We don't have any money.
We have to give them
this journal page from Dad.
Hide it!
Thanks so much for doing this.
Hey, when it comes to
His Excellency's residence,
I had them put an
extreme rush on it.
So, this is how the construction was completed?
Yeah, I don't do sloppy work.
Still, it was laid out really weird.
Usually, a wine cave is...
I don't quite understand it myself,
but those were the Führer's secretary's instructions.
The secretary is on leave,
so I am serving in her place.
Since you rushed to make the alterations, there's a little something extra in there.
Oh, there is, huh?
The Command Center
sure is generous, all right.
The construction went according to schedule.
I can't say it's reliable,
but this has to happen today.
What is it?
There's a rumor that the Elric brothers
were arrested this morning.
At least find out if the Führer is
here or not beforehand, would you?!
What could I do?!
Who knew he was going home early for his kid's birthday?!
There they are!
Don't make excuses!
Listen to reason!
Damn! Where did they go?!
Yow!
A-Are you okay?
You guys...
The impostors?
It's Russell Tringham!
They were mistaken for you guys
and got arrested.
It's a troublesome tale, what with
this much difference in our heights.
What was that?!
Huh? Have you gotten even shorter than before?
B-Brother, that was uncalled for!
What did you say?!
Be quiet, Fletcher.
The Führer suddenly
ordered them to be executed.
We thought that was too much,
and when we came to ask them what the situation was...
The commotion we caused allowed them to escape?
Are they there?!
Find them at once!
We finally meet again,
and here we have to leave right away.
Where to?
The Führer's residence, perhaps?
If that's the only place left...
U-Um...
Here.
It's part of our dad's journal.
It has something from when
he was in Central written on it.
Sensei!
Is this...
Wh-Who are you?
Frank...
Archer.
Edward Elric...
as well as the woman who got away
from the Southern Command Center...
I'll take care of this.
Go where it says in his journal.
Sensei...
Let me do something a teacher would do and get going!
You guys, too! Hurry!
From the looks of it, you didn't
have to help out here after all, Colonel.
You think they're the sort who would just quietly stay captured?
We know better than that.
We're leaving.
Sorry, but I need your car—
Fullmetal?
Colonel?
Don't tell me you're here
to capture me!
So, where are you going, Colonel?
The Wague District.
The Führer has a residence there.
What business do you have with the Führer?
I guess I don't have to ask.
Still, it must be under guard.
Major Armstrong is staging a rebellion for me.
I doubt they would even think I was in hiding in Central.
You were going to
distinguish yourself in battle
to rise to Führer, weren't you?
You also became a dog of the military
in order to attain your goal.
But then—
Lieutenant...
Just swallow all of the evil that
comes at you and realize your dream—
that's what I thought
the right way to do things was.
If you directly fight the Führer now,
you won't be in the right.
Even if you do beat him,
you'll never be able to be a leader again.
The masses won't acknowledge you.
Even so, I can't let that man
get away with it.
You're going to avenge
Lieutenant Colonel Hughes, huh?
Yeah.
He must have known everything that was going on within the military.
You're going to throw away everything you've obtained up to now for this?
No great loss.
Isn't that true for you too?
You gave up being a dog of the military for your brother's sake.
You spat up the evil you've swallowed, trying to pretend you're an adult.
Both of us are trying like little children to be faithful in living out our dreams.
You're coming with me, right?
I tried working for the military,
but I thought that wars are something
that somebody somewhere started
and ended in some place unknown to us,
and that we didn't have
anything to do with them.
But...
there's someone out there who manipulates wars to make Philosopher's Stones.
So as long as there are people
who seek the Philosopher's Stone,
the wars will continue.
And the inclination to wage them
is within all of us.
The homunculi fan the flames of war.
But it's human transmutation that creates them.
They're nothing more than what
our hearts and wits made them to be.
And if that's the case,
then there's no such thing as a war we don't have anything to do with.
But that is too much
for us to take on.
All you and I can do at any one time
is what is before us.
I'm going to find this
"you-know-who" person and defeat them.
Then I'm going to destroy the Philosopher's Stone
so that nobody will ever remember it again...
so that it will vanish from everyone's memories.
Destroy it?
The Philosopher's Stone?
Then you really did complete it?
But then, does that mean...
He's not the one who brought about
the Philosopher's Stone.
It was our hearts.
But that was your dream, wasn't it?
To use the Philosopher's Stone
to take back what you had lost?
It won't help anything if it's just our dreams that come true.
There's something more important than your dreams, huh?
There always is.
Something more important
than ourselves, or our dreams...
Farewell.
Good-bye.
Fullmetal Alchemist...
Episode 49: "The Other Side of the Gate"
On September 2nd, AD 1916,
fourteen devils shrouded the skies over London.